RG 046, Connecticut River Bridge and Highway District
Connecticut State Library
Connecticut River Bridge and Highway District records
1879-1949
Connecticut State Library
Connecticut River Bridge and Highway District
5 cubic feet
The General Assembly created the Commission in 1895 (Special Act 343) to be responsible for the construction of a new bridge over the Connecticut River to replace the wooden bridge that had burned in that year. The Commission maintained the bridge until the 1930s, when it turned its duties and title to the properties to the State and adjoining localities.
RG046
Multiple
Historical Note
The General Assembly created the Commission in 1895 (Special Act 343) to be responsible for the construction of a new bridge over the Connecticut River to replace the wooden bridge that had burned in that year. The first chair was Morgan G. Bulkeley, under whose direction the bridge was built and dedicated in October 1908. In May 1927 a second ceremony took place naming the bridge the Bulkeley Bridge. The Commission maintained the bridge until the 1930s, when it turned its duties and title to the properties to the State and adjoining localities. Final liquidation of its accounts took place on July 13, 1949, and the State Library received its remaining papers. Ella Fairchild Burr was the Commission's secretary and the architect gave her a silver punch bowl set as a token of his gratitude.
Scope and Content
Includes minutes, dedication materials, builders' bid, treasurer's reports and finanical statements, a journal, deeds and legal documents and plans, drawings and maps.
Related Material
Classified Archives, 124.2 C76d, Design, drawings, and mpas of location of Connecticut River Bridge with letter of approval, 1902-1903.
RG 006, Secretary of the State, East Hartford Bridge material, 1893-1895, Box 12. Hearing records, briefs, newspaper clippings, etc. pertaining to legislation transferring maintenance responsibility from the town to the State.
PG 475, Construction of Bulkely Bridge, East Haddam Bridge and Connecticut state Bridge, 1903-1913.
PG 480, Hartford Bridge Week Celebration, 1908.
See the online catalogue for materials on the earlier Hartford Bridge, on the legislative background of the Bulkeley Bridge (Senate Bill 27, 1895, reports) and the annual report on bridge maintenance, 1911.
Index Terms
Organizations:
Connecticut River Bridge and Highway District
Persons:
Bulkeley, Morgan G. (Morgan Gardner), 1837-1922
Places:
Hartford (Conn.)
Subjects:
Connecticut River Bridge and Highway District -- Records and correspondence; Bridges -- Connecticut; Bridges -- Connecticut River
Document Types:
Account books; Agreements; Blueprints (Reprographic copies); Correspondence; Drawings; Deeds; Ledgers (Account books); Maps; Minutes; Questionnaires
Restrictions on Access
Some of these records are stored at an off-site facility and therefore may not be available on a same-day basis.
See the policy.
Container List
- Records, 1879-1949; 1949-002
  - 1. Minutes, 1905 April-1934 October, 1936 September-1949 March; 2 looseleaf binders (Box 1)
    Also included are treasurer's and auditors' reports and other related papers.
  - 2. Dedication materials, 1909-1927 (Box 1)
    Papers pertaining to the dedication ceremonies in October 1909 and the naming ceremonies (for Morgan Bulkeley).
  - 3. Builder's bid and payment papers, 1903-1907 (Box 1)
    Detailed bod of the successful bidder, together with payment authorizations and related papers.
  - 4. Treasurer's reports and financial statements, 1895-1949 (Box 1)
    Not a complete series; others are in items 1 and 5. This group also includes papers on notes issued to Aetna Life Insurance Co.
  - 5. Journal, 1911-1949; 1 volume (Box Item 2)
    Treasurer's account book, including his annual reports, auditors reports, and other materials.
  - 5a. Ledger, 1911-1948; 1 volume (Box Item 2a)
  - 6. Deeds and other legal documents, 1879-1949 (Box 3)
    Deeds, leases, abstracts, agreements, court orders and related papers having to do with the acquisition or disposal of title or right to property, and other matters.
  - 7. Plans, drawing and maps, 1903-1949 (Box 4 (tin) and Oversize)
    Original tracings of construction drawings and blueprints of maps, plats and other materials.
    One oversize folder is with the box & specifications, 1 oversize folder is in the flat filing drawers.
    - Compromise - Plan: West Approach to River Bridge Via State Street., 1901 December; n/a; Edwin D. Graves; 30 x 95 in.; 1 inch = 40 feet
      Approved Date: 1902 February 27
      Number of work drawings: 0
    - Longitudinal Section - Stone Bridge over Connecticut River, 1903 June 19; 3; Edwin D. Graves; 30 x 80 in.in.; 1/16 inch = 1 foot
    - Profiles and Test Borings at the Location of the Proposed River Bridge, 1902 October; 2; Edwin D. Graves; 30 x 48in.; Horiziontal: 1inch = 40 feet, Vertical: 1 inch = 10 feet
    - General Plan - Stone Bridge over the Connecticut River, 1903 June 6; 1; Edwin D. Graves; 30 x 87 in.; 1/16 inch = 1 foot
    - Cross Sections at Pier and Crown - Stone Bridge over Connecticut River, 1903 June 9; 4; Edwin D. Graves; 23.5 x 30 in.; 1 inch = 4 feet
    - Details of West Abutment, 1903 June 9; 5; Edwin D. Graves; 23.5 x 30 in.; 1 inch = 8 feet
    - Details of Pier 1, 1903 June 9; 6; Edwin D. Graves; 23.5 x 30 in.; 1 inch = 8 feet
    - Details of Pier 2, 1903 June 9; 7; Edwin D. Graves; 23.5 x 30 in.; 1 inch = 8 feet
    - Details of Pier 3, 1903 June 9; 8; Edwin D. Graves; 23.5 x 30 in.; 1 inch = 8 feet
    - Details of Pier 4, 1903 June 9; 9; Edwin D. Graves; 23.5 x 30 in.; 1 inch = 8 feet
    - Details of Pier 5, 1903 June 9; 10; Edwin D. Graves; 23.5 x 30 in.; 1 inch = 8 feet
    - Details of Pier 6, 1903 June 9; 11; Edwin D. Graves; 23.5 x 30 in.; 1 inch = 8 feet
    - Details of Pier 7, 1903 June 9; 12; Edwin D. Graves; 23.5 x 30 in.; 1 inch = 8 feet
    - Details of Pier 8, 1903 June 9; 13; Edwin D. Graves; 23.5 x 30 in.; 1 inch = 8 feet
    - Details of East Abutment, 1903 June 9; 14; Edwin D. Graves; 23.5 x 30 in.; 1 inch = 8 feet
    - A - West Approach to Stone Bridge and Valley Branch NYNH & H RR, 1904 October 12; 03 A; Edwin D. Graves; 30 x 143 in.; 1 inch = 40 feet
    - C- Plan Showing Areas Affected By Proposed Exchange of Land between the Connecticut River Bridge and Highway District and NYNH & H RR Company, 1904 February 29; 05 C; Edwin D. Grave; 30 x 96 in.; 1 inch = 40 feet
    - B - Connection of New Yard with Highland Division and Windsor Street Yard., 1904 February 29; 048 B; Edwin D. Grave; 30 x 44 in.; 1 inch = 100 feet
    - E - Preliminary Survey for changing the Direction of Meadow Creek North of Highland Division of NYNH & H RR, 1904 June 1; 050 E; Edwin D. Grave; 30 x 47 in.; 1 inch = 100 feet
    - East Hartford - Property on East Bank of River, 1936 September 17; John T. Henderson; 24 x 30 in.; 1 inch = 40 feet
      Number of work drawings: 1
    - Connecticut River Bridge and Highway District Property North of Boulevard on River, East Hartford, 1935 June 5; John T. Henderson; 22/26 in.; 1 inch = 20 feet
    - Plan Showing Land to be Acquired from Connecticut River and Highway District by East Hartford Frozen Lockers, Prospect St., 1945 November; 16 x17 in.; 1 inch = 20 feet
    - Map Showing Division Line Between Land of the Connecticut River Bridge and Highway District and land of Clarence B. & Harry F. Wooldridge on North side of Connecticut Boulevard, East Hartford, 1942 January 29; C. Henry Olmstead; 10 x24 in.; 1 inch = 50 feet
    - Proposed location for East Hartford Frozen Food Lockers Prospect St., 1944 February; 16 x 16 in.; 1 inch = 20 feet
    - Property of the Connecticut River Bridge and Highway District, East Hartford, 1946 November; 18 x 24 in.; 1 inch = 40 feet
    - Connecticut River Bridge & Highway District - Plan Showing Real Estate Owned in East Hartford, 1922 December; John T Henderson; 12 x 25 in.; 1 inch = 200 feet
      Number of work drawings: 4
    - Connecticut River Bridge and Highway District Property Bounds, East Hartford, 1937 February 9; John T. Hendersson; 10 x 19 in.; 1 inch = 80 feet
    - Diagram Showing Triangular Panel of Land Adjoining property of H.E. Bidwell on the North and Running Westerly from Prospect St. at 90 degree there from, 1944 February; Charles F. Gifford; 16x16 in.; 1 inch = 20 feet
    - Connecticut River Bridge and Highway District # 1, undated; 14 x 21 in.
    - Connecticut River Bridge and Highway District # 2, undated; 14 x 21 in.
    - Connecticut River Bridge and Highway District # 3 Property owners when J.P. Sic was laid out in 1801, undated; 14 x 21 in.
    - Connecticut River Bridge and Highway District # 4 Property owners when Bridge Road was laid out., undated; 14 x 21 in.
    - Connecticut River Bridge and Highway District # 5, undated; 14 x 21 in.
    - Connecticut River Bridge and Highway District # 6, undated; n/a in.
    - Land of the Connecticut River Bridge and Highway District Conveyed to Martin J. O’Meara, 1942 February 7; C. Henry Olmstead; 9 x 11 in.; 1 inch = 50 feet
    - Property of the Connecticut River Bridge & Highway District, Connecticut Blvd., East Hartford, 1946 November; 9 x 11 in.; 1 inch = 40 feet
    - [Unidentified sketch], undated; 11 x 21 in.
- Edward W. Bush Photographs, 1899-1900, 1930-1933; 1949-001
  - Construction photographs, 1899-1900; 1 album (75 photographs) (Box 1)
  - Construction photographs, circa1930; 1 album (120 photographs) (Box 1)
  - Construction photographs, 1932-1933; 1 album (145 photographs) (Box 1)